Guide to the Glenway Wescott and Monroe Wheeler Collection of Marianne Moore
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Glenway Wescott and Monroe Wheeler collection of Marianne Moore
1923-1972
YCAL MSS 152
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.84
(2 boxes)
The collection contains miscellaneous manuscript items, notes, and ephemera related to Moore which were found among the Wescott and Wheeler papers.
Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received with the Glenway Wescott Papers and the Monroe Wheeler Papers, purchase from Monroe Wheeler, 1988, with later purchase and gift from Anatole Pohorilenko, 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Additional Marianne Moore material, including correspondence, can be found in the Glenway Wescott Papers [YCAL MSS 134] and the Monroe Wheeler Papers [YCAL MSS 136]. The materials included in this collection represent items that were already segregated when received with the original papers.
MARIANNE MOORE, 1887-1972
Marianne Moore, poet and editor of The Dial (1925-1929), was a long-time friend of Monroe Wheeler and Glenway Wescott, whom she met in the early 1920s while living in New York City.
Scope and Contents
The Glenway Wescott and Monroe Wheeler Collection of Marianne Moore contains miscellaneous manuscript items, notes, and ephemera related to Moore which were found among the Wescott and Wheeler papers. The material covers the dates 1923-72.
The collection is housed in 2 boxes and is organized into three series: I. Writings; II. Wheeler and Wescott Notes on Marianne Moore; and III. Other Material.
Series I, Writings, contains printed copies of works by Moore from newspapers and magazines, as well as two cards which reproduce Moore manuscripts, and production materials for a Museum of Modern Art book, Eight Poems, which include holograph texts in Moore's hand prepared for reproduction.
Series II, Wheeler and Wescott Notes on Marianne Moore, contains notes and journals entries made by the two men.
Series III, Other Materials, includes loose clippings, drafts of writings by Monroe Wheeler on Moore, material concerning readings, Moore memoribilia, and exhibition materials.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Wescott, Glenway, 1901-1987; Wheeler, Monroe, 1899-1988
- Writings, 1923-1972; Series I; 0.21; (.5 box)
  - Marianne Moore's "brush-off" card, printed version, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Dear St. Niklus" (1895), printed version (as greeting card), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Eight Poems, prospectus, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Eight Poems, holograph texts of poems prepared for reproduction, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Eight Poems, page proof, title and colophon only, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Eight Poems, addendum slip for "The Fish" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed copies of works by Marianne Moore, from newspapers, magazines and greeting cards, ca. 1923-67 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Wheeler and Wescott Notes on Marianne Moore, 1949-1972; Series II; 0.21; (.5 box)
  - Glenway Wescott's folder of notes and clippings about Marianne Moore, ca. 1951-67 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Monroe Wheeler's notes and journal entries on Marianne Moore, ca. 1949-72 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
- Other Material, 1957-1990; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Clippings re: Marianne Moore, 1957-90 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Envelopes, annotated, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Introduction of Marianne Moore by Monroe Wheeler at the National Academy of Arts and Letters, drafts, typescript and carbon, corrected, 1962 Nov (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Invitations to exhibitions at Rosenbach Library, 1972, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - National Book Committee program, including presentation of National Medal for Literature to Marianne Moore, 1968 Dec 10 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Invitation, program and catalog for Marianne Moore reading, Poetry magazine poetry day, 1961 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Obituary of Marianne Moore by Monroe Wheeler for Yale publication, drafts, typescript carbon and photocopy, 1972 Feb 26 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Marianne Moore items in Phoenix Book Shop catalog, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Marianne Moore postage stamp on envelope, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Tickets to Marianne Moore reading at YMHA, 1964 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Introduction to Marianne Moore reading (at YMHA?) by Monroe Wheeler, reading text, ca. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Reminiscence", (altered version of introduction to YMHA reading) by Monroe Wheeler, draft, typescript, photocopy and galley proof, corrected, photocopy, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Questions submitted to Marianne Moore after her reading at YMHA, 1964 Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Poster: "May is Senior Citizens Month in New York State" featuring Marianne Moore, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Recipe from Marianne Moore: Beaten egg and oil dressing (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Recording [cassette tape] of Marianne Moore reading "Marriage", 1953 Nov 7 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes letter from David Schmerler to Monroe Wheeler, 1987 Oct 27
  - "Vision into Verse" exhibition at Rosenbach Library, proof pages, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)